Register of the Innokentii Nikolaevich Seryshev Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Innokentii Nikolaevich Seryshev papers
1891-1968
2000C23
Hoover Institution Archives
20 microfilm reels (3 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the Russian Orthodox Church abroad, Russian émigré affairs, and the promotion of Esperanto.
Seryshev, Innokentii Nikolaevich, b. 1883
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Father Innokentii Seryshev was born on 14 August 1883 in the village of Bol'shaia Kudara, in the Trans-Baikal region. In 1902 he married Ekaterina Fedorovna Bondarenko. From 1906 to 1909 he was the village priest in Doronino, and from 1910 to 1913 in Shergol'dzhin, both in the Trans-Baikal region. It was in this period that he became interested in Esperanto, a language he spent most of the rest of his life promoting. From 1917 to 1919 he was a member of the board of directors of the Soiuz kul'turno-prosvetitel'nykh obshchestv Altaiskogo kraia.
From 1920 to 1922, Seryshev was in Japan, where he made a study of the Japanese educational system (published in his Strana samuraev, 1924). Thereafter, from 1922 to 1924, he lived in Harbin and Peking, where he taught in the railroad school and at the Chinese Esperanto College. In 1925 Seryshev emigrated to Australia, where he was a parish priest in Sydney and editor and chief writer for a number of secular and religious periodicals: Aziia, Put' emigranta, Tserkov' i nauka, and others (including some in Esperanto). He also compiled a biographical dictionary of prominent Russians, entitled Great, Outstanding, and Eminent Personalities of Russia (1945-1946). Seryshev died in Australia in 1976.
Chronology
1883 August 14 Born, Bol'shaia Kudara village, Zabaikal district, Russia
1902 Married Ekaterina Fedorovna Bondarenko
1906-1909 Priest, Doronino (Zabaikal district)
1910-1913 Priest, Shergol'dzhin (Zabaikal district)
1917-1919 Member, Board of Directors, Soiuz kul'turno-prosvetitel'nykh obshchestv Altaiskogo kraia
1920-1922 Studied educational system in Japan
1922-1924 Taught in the railroad school, Harbin, China
1924 Taught in the Chinese Esperanto College, Peking, China Author, Strana samuraev
1925-1965 Priest and editor of religious and secular periodicals (some in Esperanto) in Sydney, Australia
1976 August 23 Died, Australia
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of the papers of Rev. Innokentii Seryshev, a Russian Orthodox priest active in the first half of the 20 th century in Siberia, Japan, China and Australia. Of particular interest is his hobby: the study of Esperanto, of which he was a devoted adherent. Some correspondence and publications are in that language ( Oriento, La Pacifiko, and other works in the Speeches and Writings series), and there is a written work on its development in Russian and the USSR ("Esperanto v S.S.S.R.," Box 11, Folder 7).
The materials in the collection reflect mainly his involvement in émigré and Church affairs, mainly in China and Australia, and include correspondence with prominent émigré figures as well as materials for a biographical encyclopedia of prominent Russians that included a large number of émigrés. Also valuable are his multi-volume memoirs, "V zemnom plane moego vechnogo bytiia."
A significant part of the collection consists of periodicals edited and published by Seryshev, on both religious and secular themes, most of which are in mimeograph or similar format, and there is a large amount of writings on religious issues: sermons, apologetics, etc.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming of these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives.
Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'.; Australia.; China.; Esperanto.; Japan.; Russia.; Russians in foreign countries.
- Biographical File, 1918-[1965] (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of bibliography of writings and periodicals edited, and scrapbooks containing correspondence, identity and travel papers, as well as other documents. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1915-1955 (Box 1)
  Scrapbooks and loose correspondence filed alphabetically by correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1920-1968 (Box 2-11)
  Arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, 1891-1951 (Box 11-12)
  Correspondence, clippings, scrapbooks, speeches and writings, arranged alphabetically by subject. Includes biographical dossiers on various significant Russian émigrés
- Printed Matter, 1904-1969 (Box 12)
  Primarily religious literature, including church and parish bulletins, arranged in alphabetical order by title
- Photographs, 1916-1953 (Box 13)
  Include paste-ups for Seryshev's publications as well as group photos of Russian and foreign Esperantists, including Seryshev
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1918-[1965] (Box 1)
  - Autobiography.
    General note
    See SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/"V zemnom plane moego vechnogo bytiia"
  - Bibliographical list of Seryshev's publications, [1965] (Folder 1: 1)
  - Scrapbooks
    - "Delo o deiatel'nosti i rabote sviashchennika Innokentiia Serysheva na Altae (Sibir') v dni po-Fevral'skoi revoliutsii i o poezdke ego v Iaponiiu po prichine padeniia Kolchakovskogo rezhima i nastupleniia rezhima bol'shevikov,"., 1918-1948 (Folder 1: 2)
      Consists of correspondence, identity papers, travel certificates, orders, and related materials. Includes introductory note and index
    - "Delo o prebyvanii sviashchennika Innokentiia Serysheva v Kharbine,"., 1922-1948 (Folder 1: 3)
      Consists of correspondence, writings and printed matter. Includes introductory note
    - "Dela Sidneiskogo prikhoda i rol' sviashch. I. Serysheva v nem,"., 1921-1949 (Folder 1: 4)
      Consists of autobiographical note, correspondence, circulars, and related matter
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1915-1955
  See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Scrapbooks, SPEECHES AND WRITINGS (esp. "V zemnom plane moego vechnogo bytiia"), and SUBJECT FILE
  - General--Scrapbooks
    - File 1, 1915-1944 (Folder 1: 5)
      Correspondents include K. V. Baturin, Bishop Vasilii, Sergei Maslov, and V. Zenzinov. Includes index as well as related printed matter
    - File 2, 1929-1949 (Folder 1: 6)
      Correspondents include G. D. Grebenshchikov and S. I. Gusev-Orenburgskii. Includes index
    - "Delovaia perepiska,"., 1936-1952 (Folder 1: 7)
      Correspondents include Bishop Serafim, N. N. Alekseev, A. V. Treichke
    - "Sviaz' s redaktsiiami i izdatel'stvami,", 1943-1947 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Agreneva-Slavianskaia, Margarita, D., 1947 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Bulgakov, Petr I.
    See SUBJECT FILE
  - Korzhenevskii, Pavel Vasil'evich, 1937-1948 (Folder 1: 10)
    Includes postcards from Korzhenevskii's children
  - Morita, Pavel, 1920 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Sergii, Bishop of Japan, 1920 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Shkurkin, Pavel Vasil'evich.
  - Zarochentsev, Mikhail Trofimovich, 1953-1955 (Folder 1: 13)
  - SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1920-1968 (Box 2)
    For other works printed by his publishing house, see SUBJECT FILE
    Includes periodicals edited by Seryshev, nearly every issue of which contain one or more of his articles.
  - General
    - General
      - Untitled compilation of articles and fragments of articles from various journals (Folder 2: 1)
        Printed copy
      - "Sbornik broshiur Izdatel'stva 'Oriento',"., 1935-1941 (Folder 2: 2)
        Printed copy. Bound compilation of brochures (with table of contents) issued by Seryshev, some as supplements to his periodicals
    - Scrapbook. "Stat'i I. Serysheva, pisannye iz Iaponii, po raznym voprosam, v esperantskikh zhurnalakh na Esperanto i v iaponskikh po-iaponski i po-russki, ", 1920-1922 (Folder 2: 3)
      Articles in periodical press include primarily works on Esperanto (in La Orienta Lumo, La Revuo Orienta, La Verda Ombro and other periodicals), as well as on current events (in Golos Iaponii)
    - Tables of contents to some issues of periodicals edited and published by Seryshev (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Liubopytnyi dokument,"., 1921 January 1 (Folder 2: 5)
    Typescript
  - "Lektsiia Episkopa Sergiia ob arkhiepiskope iaponskom Nikolae," [summary]., 1922
    See SUBJECT FILE/Bulgakov, Petr/Subject file
  - "Sushchnost' velikogo narodnogo vosstaniia v Sibiri v godu,"., 1919 1922 (Folder 2: 6)
    Holograph
  - "Iz vpechatlenii o Iaponii,"., 1924 (Folder 2: 7)
    Printed copy. Clippings from an unidentified Harbin newspaper ( Nasha zaria?)
  - Strana samuraev, 1924-1925
    - Part I. (Folder 2: 8)
      Includes Takekuma Tokusaburo, Aborigeny ostrova Khokkaido - "Ainy", translated by I. Seryshev. Printed copy
    - Part II
      - Holograph. (Folder 2: 9)
        Includes introductory note by Seryshev, 1948 May
      - Printed copy (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Oriento, #1., (July 1925) (Folder 3: 2)
    Printed copy. Includes table of contents to numbers 1-2 (typescript and holograph)
  - Tserkovnyi kolokol (periodical).
    - (#1) - (#2), 1932 May April (Folder 3: 3)
    - (#1) - (#4), 1932 November 1933 February (Folder 3: 4)
  - Tserkov' i nauka (periodical).
    - (#1) - (#10), 1933 March 1933 December (Folder 3: 5)
    - (#11) - (#22), 1934 January 1934 December (Folder 3: 6)
    - (#23) - (#30), 1935 January 1935 August (Folder 3: 7)
    - (#32) - (#37), 1935 October 1936 March (Folder 3: 8)
    - Fragments of #43; #52, (1936) (1954) (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Polemicheskii biulleten', (#1) (periodical)., 1933 July (Folder 4: 2)
  - Avstralaziia, (#1) - (#3) (periodical)., 1933 November 1935 April-September (Folder 4: 3)
  - Aziia, (#1); (#2); (#3) (periodical)., 1934 March 1935 January 1937 April [1935 December] (Folder 4: 4)
  - Informatsionnyi biulleten' Izdatel'stva "Oriento", #1., (May 1935) (Folder 4: 5)
  - Put' emigranta (periodical).
    - (#4) - (#3/9), 1935 October 1936 March (Folder 4: 6)
    - (#4) - (#19), 1936 April 1937 February (Folder 4: 7)
    - (#20) - (#29), 1937 March 1937 December (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - (#30) - (#37), 1938 January 1938 August (Folder 5: 2)
    - (#38) - (#46), 1938 September 1941 July (Folder 5: 3)
  - La Pacifiko, (#1) - (#2), 1935 December 1936 September (Folder 5: 4)
  - "Al'bom 'Avstralaziia',"., 1937-1940 (Folder 5: 5)
  - "Lektsionnyi al'manakh russkogo doma v Sidnee za 1943 god,". (Folder 5: 6)
    Printed copy. Includes lectures by others
  - Album of Great, Outstanding and Eminent Personalities of Russia, 1945-1946
    - Background materials. (Folder 5: 7)
      For additional photostats, see PHOTOGRAPHS
      Include clippings, correspondence, notes, photographs.
    - Background materials (Box-folder 6: 1-7)
    - Background materials (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Progress reports (Folder 7: 2)
    - Drafts (Folder 7: 3-8)
    - Printed copy, parts I-III (Folder 7: 9)
    - Reviews. (Folder 7: 10-11)
      Includes newspaper clippings and correspondence, 1945-1954
  - Review of V. Krymov, Drozofily i my, 1948 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - "Religiia i nauka,"., 1948 (Folder 8: 2)
  - "Strastnaia sedmitsa,"., 1948 (Folder 8: 3)
  - "Mozhet byt' ili navernost',"., 1949 April (Folder 8: 4)
  - "Problema mehdunarodnogo iazyka,"., 1949 August (Folder 8: 5)
  - "Paskha,"., 1949 September (Folder 8: 6)
  - "Mysli o sektantstve,"., 1949 November (Folder 8: 7)
  - "Chetvertoe imerenie prostranstva,"., [1950 January] (Folder 8: 8)
  - "Zagrobnaia zhizn',"., 1950 September (Folder 8: 9)
  - "Bog, mir, chelovek,"., 1951 (Folder 8: 10)
  - Missionerskii listok, 1951 September - [1966] (Folder 8: 11)
  - "Sbornik propovedei, besed i tem dlia dukhovnykh lektsii v pomoshch' pravoslavnym pastyriam,"., 1951 December (Folder 8: 12)
  - "V zemnom plane moego vechnogo bytiia,"., 1952 February - 1968 (Box 9)
    Typescript. Includes photographs of author and others
    - Volume 1: "V Sibiri." (Folder 9: 1)
      Missing pp. 281-282, 355-356
    - Volume 2: "V Iaponii" (Folder 9: 2)
    - Volume 3: "V Kitae" (Folder 9: 3)
    - Volume 4: "V Avstralii" (Folder 9: 4)
    - Volume 4: "V Avstralii (Folder 10: 1-2)
    - Volume 4: "V Avstralii." (Folder 10: 3-4)
      Appendices (correspondence, documents and photographs)
    - Volume 5: "Moi lektsii, doklady, stat'i" (Folder 10: 5)
    - Conclusion, table of contents, bibliography of Seryshev's works (Folder 10: 6)
  - "Rabota russkikh emigrantov na internatsional'nom poprishche esperantizma,"., 1952 December (Folder 10: 7)
  - Lechebnyi sbornik, #2., (1954) (Folder 10: 8)
    Printed copy. Compiled and edited by Seryshev.
  - V chasy dosuga, v minuty razdum'ia, (#18-19), 1955-1957 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - "Istoriia Sidneiskogo prikhoda ot ego osnovaniia do pribytiia pervogo episkopa,"., 1956 July (Folder 11: 2)
  - Kriticheskii sbornik #3: Teosofiia, okkul'tim i khristianstvo, 1959 February (Folder 11: 3)
  - Mia "Cigna Kanto"/ Moia lebedinaia pesn', 1960 March (Folder 11: 4)
  - Voco de Esperantulo/ Golos Esperantista,, unnumbered issue., 1962 (#1) and undated (Folder 11: 5)
  - Sperto de mia vivo, 1962 May (Folder 11: 6)
  - "Esperanto v S.S.S.R. i v ee satelitakh: Chast' 2-ia,", 1962 August (Folder 11: 7)
  - Opisanie zhini matushki Ekateriny Feodorovny Seryshevoi, 1964 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Apologeticheskie uroki Vetkhogo Zaveta, parts 1-7, 1966-1967 (Folder 11: 9)
  - Kritika knigi frantsuza ateista Leo Taksil' "Zabavnaia Bibliia,"., 1968 August (Folder 11: 10)
  - "Na knizhku 'Vo svete pisaniia' ukrainskogo eks-iereia G. Dobrovol'skogo, ushedshego v sektu baptistov, moi kriticheskii otvet,"., 1968 August (Folder 11: 11)
  - "Ob"iasnenie liturgii dlia molodezhi,"., 1968 December (Folder 11: 12)
  - "Potemkinskie potemki: Kriticheskii otvet na broshiuru starovera K. V. Potemkina 'Raz"ediniaiushchaia sila',"., 1968 December (Folder 11: 13)
  - "O reforme nashego eparkhial'nogo zhurnala,"., 1968 December 25 (Folder 11: 14)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1891-1951
  - Bebutova, Olga. (Folder 11: 15)
    Consists of letters from Archbishop Feodosii to Seryshev, 1951, and receipts pertaining to Seryshev's activity in advancing financial aid to Bebutova
  - Bulgakov, Petr, Rev.
    Materials from Bulgakov's archive sent to Seryshev, consisting of his correspondence, writings, and collected materials
    - Biographical file. (Folder 11: 16)
      Includes brief notes and chronology of Bulgakov's life
    - Correspondence
      - General
        - General and unidentified, [1908]-1928 and undated (Folder 11: 17)
        - Scrapbook. (Folder 11: 18)
          Includes letters to Seryshev, Patriarch Tikhon and others, 1922-1930 and undated. Also includes photograph of Bulgakov and biographical introduction by Seryshev, dated 1948
      - Sergii, Bishop of Japan, 1920-1930 (Folder 11: 19)
      - Seryshev, Innokentii, 1920-1930 (Folder 11: 20)
      - Tikhon, Patriarch, 1891-1923 (Folder 11: 21)
        Includes letter by S. Bulgakova to Seryshev introducing this correspondence, 1939
    - Subject file - Sergii, Bishop of Japan. (Folder 11: 22)
      Includes summary of speech by him written by Seryshev and related letter by Bulgakov to the newspaper Novaia zaria, 1931
    - Writings, 1908-1930 (Folder 11: 23)
      May include pieces not by Bulgakov
    - Miscellany (Folder 11: 24)
  - Japanese students. (Box-folder 12: 1)
    Diary of a Japanese student studying the Russian language, 1919-1920
  - Russians--Australia. (Folder 12: 2)
    Scrapbook includes correspondence with A. A. Faminskii, 1939, and others, clippings, broadsides and other materials relating to Russians in Australia in the 1920s-1930s
  - Shkurkin, Pavel Vasil'evich. (Folder 12: 3)
    Correspondence, 1927-1941, clippings, photograph and collected materials relating to the biography of this orientalist
  - Miscellany. (Folder 12: 4)
    Includes newspaper clippings, mainly on church affairs
  - PRINTED MATTER, 1904-1969 (Folder 12: 5-8)
    Consists mainly of religious literature, including a large amount of bulletins issued by various parishes and organizations in China and Australia, some published by Seryshev, as well as mimeographed and typed reports on religious and church-related subjects
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1916-1953 (Box 13)
  - Photostats for use in Seryshev's Album of Great, Outstanding and Eminent Personalities (Folder 13: 1)
  - Postcards, depicting various subjects, including indigenous peoples of Australasia. (Folder 13: 2)
    Include many printed by Seryshev, with titles in Esperanto
  - Esperanto groups (including Seryshev) in Barnaul, Russia,, and Peking, 1916 1924 (Folder 13: 3)